Puerto Rican Collection
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Puerto Rican Collection 1591-1900 (bulk 1750-1898)
MSS80481
1,000 items
12 containers plus 1 oversize
5 linear feet
2 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Collection of documents from Spanish colonial Puerto Rico including financial material, military papers, orders and decrees from the Spanish government, and miscellaneous items from colonial Puerto Rico.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Coll y Toste, Cayetano, 1850-1930. Cayetano Coll y Toste collection relating to Puerto Rico, 1850-1894.
Organizations
Puerto Rico.; Spain. Ministerio de la Guerra--History.
Subjects
Baptismal records--Puerto Rico.; Education--Puerto Rico.; Exports--Puerto Rico.; Finance, Public--Puerto Rico.; Fortification--Puerto Rico.; Imports--Puerto Rico.; Noncitizens--Puerto Rico.; Political prisoners--Puerto Rico.; Slavery--Puerto Rico.; Spanish-American War, 1898--Puerto Rico.; Taxation--Puerto Rico.
Places
Morro (San Juan, P.R.); Puerto Rico--Commerce.; Puerto Rico--History, Military.; Puerto Rico--History--To 1898.; Puerto Rico--Politics and government--To 1898.; Puerto Rico.; Spain--Colonies--America.
Provenance
The first part of the Puerto Rican Collection was received by the Library of Congress from the War Department after the American occupation of San Juan following the Spanish-American War. Manuscripts from other sources were added to the collection over the years, most notably by gift from the Puerto Rican historian, writer, and government official Cayetano Coll y Toste, 1899-1900. An addition was given by J. H. Hollander in 1908 and by Victor S. Clark in 1928. In 2011, the Cayetano Coll y Toste Collection Relating to Puerto Rico which had also been acquired in 1899-1900 was united with other material received from him and organized as part of this colleciton.
Additional Guides
The Puerto Rican collection is described in the Library's 1918 Handbook of Manuscripts, 527-529.
Access and Restrictions
The Puerto Rican Collection is open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Microfilm
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on two reels. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan. To promote preservation of the originals, researchers are required to consult the microfilm edition as available.
Scope and Content Note
The Puerto Rican Collection spans the years 1591-1900, with the bulk of the material dating from 1750 to 1898. The papers are in Spanish with some English. The papers contain documents from the Spanish colonial government of Puerto Rico including financial material reflecting budgets, data on imports and exports, and taxation, military papers from the War Ministry, and orders and decrees from the Spanish government. A wide variety of other papers document other aspects of Spanish colonial Puerto Rico including items concerning slavery, political prisoners, registration of foreigners, the fortifications of “El Morro” in San Juan, baptismal records, and politics. Many of these items had belonged to the Puerto Rican writer, historian, and government official Cayetano Coll y Toste and relate to his research interests. A very few items, mostly concerning education, date from after the Spanish-American War and the subsequent American occupation of Puerto Rico.
Arrangement of the Papers
This collection is organized by topic or type of material.
Container List
- Facsimile de la primera fortificatión levantada en el Morro de San Juan de Puerto Rico, (original dated Aug. 10, 1591), 1899 (Box 1)
- Office of Finance records, 1766-1798 (Box 1)
- Budgets and financial information, Spanish colonial government of Puerto Rico, 1850, 1881-1886, (4 volumes) (Box 2)
- Printed matter and miscellany, 1894-1898 (Box 2)
- Royal orders to the governor, 1786-1789 (Box 3)
- Real Provisión, 1790 (Box 3)
- Revolutionary literature and letters sent to Ponce, Puerto Rico, from Puerto Cabello and La Guaira, Venezuela, 1863-1865, (2 folders) (Box 3)
- Miscellany, undated (Box 3)
- Angelis, Pedro, “Para mi Revista,” 1810-1814 (Box 3)
- Baptismal records, 1645-1646, 1647, 1653 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous treasury statements and financial papers, 1796-1857 (Box 4)
- Sala, Valentin, revolutionary conditions in Venezuela and the Caribbean 1812 (Box 4)
- Spanish army in Puerto Rico, 1813-1814, (2 folders) (Box 4)
- Decretos del Rey Fernando VII 1814-1844, (1 vol.) (Box 4)
- Decretos del Rey Fernando VII 1814-1844, (1 vol.) (Box 5)
- Correspondence of the war minister, 1815-1819 (Box 5)
- Daily record, War Office, 1816-1817 (Box 6)
- Proclamation “Habitantes de Puerto Rico,” 1823 (Box 6)
- Lottery tickets, 1830 (Box 6)
- Presupuesto de la Isla de Puerto Rico, 1850 (Box 6)
- Negros Emancipados Filiaciones, 1859 (Box 7)
  Available on microfilm shelf no.17,433
- Rodriguez, Valentín, passport, 1852 (Box 8)
- Libreta del journalero Manuel Camacho, 1869 (Box 8)
- “Libro de actas de la Junta... de la esclavitud," 1874 (Box 8)
- “Memoria sobre el servicio de Telégrafo de la Isla de Puerto Rico en 1875 a 1876, 1877 a 1878," 1878 (Box 8)
- Gobierno Superior Civil de la Provincia de Puerto Rico, register of foreigners, 1870-1875 (Box 8)
  Available on microfilm shelf no. 17,777
- Letter to the governor, Puerto Rico, 1896-1898 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous financial papers, 1896-1898 (Box 9)
- “The Money Question,” 1895, (3 folders) (Box 9)
- “Report on Puerto Rico Money,” 1893 (Box 9)
- “Reply to Report by the Representatives of the Gas Company,” 1895 (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous reports, 1895, (3 folders) (Box 9)
- Miscellaneous broadsides and pamphlets, 1886-1898, (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Puerto Rico lottery, 1880, (2 folders) (Box 9)
- Puerto Rico lottery, 1880, (1 folder) (Box 10)
- Gobierno General de la Isla de Puerto Rico, prisoner transfer, 1887 (Box 10)
- Stamped paper, 1882-1900 (Box 10)
- Education, 1898-1900, (4 folders) (Box 10)
- Statistics, financial and commercial, 1850-1899 (Box 11)
- Postage stamps, 1891-1894, (4 folders) (Box 11)
- La Real Tesorería de Puerto Rico, bank notes, nineteenth century (Box 11)
- Puerto Rico lottery, 1830 (Box 11)
- Vidal y Martorell, Juan, relative to Joaquín Baco and Juan Antonio Negroín, circa 1876 (Box 11)
- Miscellany, unknown source, undated (Box 11)
- Ambulance Corps for American Expeditionary Forces, undated (Box 12)
- Gumien, Francisco, Alcaidía Municipal de Hato Grande to director of Royal Academy of Literature, undated (Box 12)
- Bermudes, Matías, and Pablo Boada regarding Juan Jesús Rodriguez, Nov. 15, 1852 (Box 12)
- Alonzo, Juan, to governor general of province of Puerto Rico, Sept. 28, 1876 (Box 12)
- Sevilla, Rafael de, 1846 (Box 12)
- Cortego, Santiago, Comandancia de Injenieros to Santiago Fortum, Aug. 17, 1846 (Box 12)
- Garcia, Domingo, to Santiago Fortum, Aug. 17, 1846 (Box 12)
- Deofeda, Juan Calisto, to Santiago Fortum, Aug. 16, 1846 (Box 12)
- Meléndez, Salvador, Feb.-Apr., 1812 (Box 12)
- Miscellany, unknown source, undated (Box 12)
- Oversize copies of miscellaneous orders, affidavits, and royal cédulas, 1750-1757 (Box OV 1)